Processes and threads
A process is an executing program. An operating system uses processes to
separate the applications that are being executed. A thread is the basic
unit to which an operating system allocates processor time. Each thread has
a scheduling priority and maintains a set of structures the system uses to
save the thread context when the thread's execution is paused. The thread
context includes all the information the thread needs to seamlessly resume
execution, including the thread's set of CPU registers and stack. Multiple
threads can run in the context of a process. All threads of a process share
its virtual address space. A thread can execute any part of the program
code, including parts currently being executed by another thread.

By default, a .NET program is started with a single thread, often called
the primary thread. However, it can create additional threads to execute
code in parallel or concurrently with the primary thread. These threads are
often called worker threads. When to use multiple threads You use multiple
threads to increase the responsiveness of your application and to take
advantage of a multiprocessor or multi-core system to increase the
application's throughput. Consider a desktop application, in which the
primary thread is responsible for user interface elements and responds to
user actions. Use worker threads to perform time-consuming operations that,
otherwise, would occupy the primary thread and make the user interface
non-responsive. You can also use a dedicated thread for network or device
communication to be more responsive to incoming messages or events. If your
program performs operations that can be done in parallel, the total
execution time can be decreased by performing those operations in separate
threads and running the program on a multiprocessor or multi-core system.
On such a system, use of multithreading might increase throughput along
with the increased responsiveness. How to use multithreading in .NET
Starting with .NET Framework 4, the recommended way to utilize
multithreading is to use Task Parallel Library (TPL) and Parallel LINQ
(PLINQ). For more information, see Parallel programming. Both TPL and PLINQ
rely on the ThreadPool threads. The System.Threading.ThreadPool class
provides a .NET application with a pool of worker threads. You can also use
thread pool threads. For more information, see The managed thread pool. At
last, you can use the System.Threading.Thread class that represents a
managed thread. For more information, see Using threads and threading.
Multiple threads might need to access a shared resource. To keep the
resource in an uncorrupted state and avoid race conditions, you must
synchronize the thread access to it. You also might want to coordinate the
interaction of multiple threads. .NET provides a range of types that you
can use to synchronize access to a shared resource or coordinate thread
interaction. For more information, see Overview of synchronization
primitives. Do handle exceptions in threads. Unhandled exceptions in
threads generally terminate the process. For more information, see
Exceptions in managed threads.

Exceptions in managed threads 

The common language runtime allows most
unhandled exceptions in threads to proceed naturally. In most cases, this
means that the unhandled exception causes the application to terminate.
However, the common language runtime provides a backstop for certain
unhandled exceptions that are used for controlling program flow: A
ThreadAbortException is thrown in a thread because Abort was called. This
only applies to .NET Framework apps. An AppDomainUnloadedException is
thrown in a thread because the application domain in which the thread is
executing is being unloaded. The common language runtime or a host process
terminates the thread by throwing an internal exception. If any of these
exceptions are unhandled in threads created by the common language runtime,
the exception terminates the thread, but the common language runtime does
not allow the exception to proceed further. If these exceptions are
unhandled in the main thread, or in threads that entered the runtime from
unmanaged code, they proceed normally, resulting in termination of the
application. 

Note 

It's possible for the runtime to throw an unhandled
exception before any managed code has had a chance to install an exception
handler. Even though managed code had no chance to handle such an
exception, the exception is allowed to proceed naturally. 

Expose threading
problems during development When threads are allowed to fail silently,
without terminating the application, serious programming problems can go
undetected. This is a particular problem for services and other
applications that run for extended periods. As threads fail, program state
gradually becomes corrupted. Application performance may degrade, or the
application might become unresponsive. Allowing unhandled exceptions in
threads to proceed naturally, until the operating system terminates the
program, exposes such problems during development and testing. Error
reports on program terminations support debugging. Host override An
unmanaged host can use the ICLRPolicyManager interface in the Hosting API
to override the default unhandled exception policy of the common language
runtime. The ICLRPolicyManager::SetUnhandledExceptionPolicy function is
used to set the policy for unhandled exceptions.

Synchronizing data for multithreading

When multiple threads can make calls to the properties and methods of a
single object, it is critical that those calls be synchronized. Otherwise
one thread might interrupt what another thread is doing, and the object
could be left in an invalid state. A class whose members are protected from
such interruptions is called thread-safe. .NET provides several strategies
to synchronize access to instance and static members: Synchronized code
regions. You can use the Monitor class or compiler support for this class
to synchronize only the code block that needs it, improving performance.
Manual synchronization. You can use the synchronization objects provided by
the .NET class library. See Overview of Synchronization Primitives, which
includes a discussion of the Monitor class. Synchronized contexts. For .NET
Framework and Xamarin applications only, you can use the
SynchronizationAttribute to enable simple, automatic synchronization for
ContextBoundObject objects. Collection classes in the
System.Collections.Concurrent namespace. These classes provide built-in
synchronized add and remove operations. For more information, see
Thread-Safe Collections. The common language runtime provides a thread
model in which classes fall into a number of categories that can be
synchronized in a variety of different ways depending on the requirements.
The following table shows what synchronization support is provided for
fields and methods with a given synchronization category. No
synchronization This is the default for objects. Any thread can access any
method or field at any time. Only one thread at a time should access these
objects. Manual synchronization The .NET class library provides a number of
classes for synchronizing threads. See Overview of Synchronization
Primitives. Synchronized code regions You can use the Monitor class or a
compiler keyword to synchronize blocks of code, instance methods, and
static methods. There is no support for synchronized static fields. Both
Visual Basic and C# support the marking of blocks of code with a particular
language keyword, the lock statement in C# or the SyncLock statement in
Visual Basic. When the code is executed by a thread, an attempt is made to
acquire the lock. If the lock has already been acquired by another thread,
the thread blocks until the lock becomes available. When the thread exits
the synchronized block of code, the lock is released, no matter how the
thread exits the block. Note Beginning in C# 13, the lock statement
recognizes if the locked object is an instance of System.Threading.Lock and
uses the EnterScope method to create a synchronized region. The lock, when
the target isn't a Lock instance, and SyncLock statements are implemented
using Monitor.Enter and Monitor.Exit, so other methods of Monitor can be
used in conjunction with them within the synchronized region. You can also
decorate a method with a MethodImplAttribute with a value of
MethodImplOptions.Synchronized, which has the same effect as using Monitor
or one of the compiler keywords to lock the entire body of the method.
Thread.Interrupt can be used to break a thread out of blocking operations
such as waiting for access to a synchronized region of code.
Thread.Interrupt is also used to break threads out of operations like
Thread.Sleep. 

Important 

Do not lock the type — that is, typeof(MyType) in
C#, GetType(MyType) in Visual Basic, or MyType::typeid in C++ — in order to
protect static methods (Shared methods in Visual Basic). Use a private
static object instead. Similarly, do not use this in C# (Me in Visual
Basic) to lock instance methods. Use a private object instead. A class or
instance can be locked by code other than your own, potentially causing
deadlocks or performance problems. 

Compiler support Both Visual Basic and
C# support a language keyword that uses Monitor.Enter and Monitor.Exit to
lock the object. Visual Basic supports the SyncLock statement; C# supports
the lock statement. In both cases, if an exception is thrown in the code
block, the lock acquired by the lock or SyncLock is released automatically.
The C# and Visual Basic compilers emit a try/finally block with
Monitor.Enter at the beginning of the try, and Monitor.Exit in the finally
block. If an exception is thrown inside the lock or SyncLock block, the
finally handler runs to allow you to do any clean-up work. Synchronized
Context In .NET Framework and Xamarin applications only, you can use the
SynchronizationAttribute on any ContextBoundObject to synchronize all
instance methods and fields. All objects in the same context domain share
the same lock. Multiple threads are allowed to access the methods and
fields, but only a single thread is allowed at any one time.

Foreground and background threads
A managed thread is either a background thread or a foreground thread.
Background threads are identical to foreground threads with one exception:
a background thread does not keep the managed execution environment
running. Once all foreground threads have been stopped in a managed process
(where the .exe file is a managed assembly), the system stops all
background threads and shuts down. 

Note 

When the runtime stops a background
thread because the process is shutting down, no exception is thrown in the
thread. However, when threads are stopped because the AppDomain.Unload
method unloads the application domain, a ThreadAbortException is thrown in
both foreground and background threads. Use the Thread.IsBackground
property to determine whether a thread is a background or a foreground
thread, or to change its status. A thread can be changed to a background
thread at any time by setting its IsBackground property to true. 

Important

The foreground or background status of a thread does not affect the outcome
of an unhandled exception in the thread. An unhandled exception in either
foreground or background threads results in termination of the application.
See Exceptions in Managed Threads. 

Threads that belong to the managed
thread pool (that is, threads whose IsThreadPoolThread property is true)
are background threads. All threads that enter the managed execution
environment from unmanaged code are marked as background threads. All
threads generated by creating and starting a new Thread object are by
default foreground threads. If you use a thread to monitor an activity,
such as a socket connection, set its IsBackground property to true so that
the thread does not prevent your process from terminating.
